<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>NO TITLE</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>No publication information is avaliable</p>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Produced by: Adobe Acrobat 9.0 Paper Capture Plug-in</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Generated from a source PDF document</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date>2010-08-11T06:44:53 -0400</date>
	      Created by: Adobe Acrobat 9.0</creation>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2010-08-11T06:45:59 -0400</date>
<respStmt>
<name>unknown person</name>
</respStmt>
<item>unknown changes</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 id="page_1" n="1" type="page">
<p>Common-Sense Religion 
By Daniel C. Dennett 
A
CORDING TO SURVEYS, most of the people in the 
world say that religion is very important 
in their lives. Many would say that with 
out it, their lives would be meaningless. 
It's tempting just to take them at their 
word, to declare that nothing more is to be said-and 
to tiptoe away. Who would want to interfere with 
whatever it is that gives their lives meaning? But if we 
do that, we willfully ignore some serious questions. 
Can just any religion give lives meaning, in a way that 
we should honor and respect? What about people 
who fall into the clutches of cult leaders, or who are 
duped into giving their life savings to religious con 
artists? Do their lives still have meaning, even though 
their particular "religion" is a fraud? 
In Marjoe, the 1972 documentary about the bogus 
evangelist Marjoe Gortner, we see poor people empty 
ing their wallets and purses into the collection plate, 
their eyes glistening with tears of joy, thrilled to be get 
ting "salvation" from the charismatic phony. The ques 
tion that has been troubling me ever since I first saw the 
film is: Who is cOmmitting the more reprehensible act 
Gortner, who lies to people to get their money, or the 
filmmakers who expose the lies (with Gortner's enthusi 
astic complicity), thereby robbing the good folk of the 
meaning they thought they had found for their lives? 
Consid&lt;:r what their lives may be like (I am imagining 
the details, which are not in the documentary): Sam is a 
high-school dropout, pumping gas at the station at the 
crossroads and hoping someday to buy a motorcycle; he 
is a Dallas Cowboys fan, and likes to have a few beers 
while watching the games on television. Lucille, who 
never mamed, is in charge of the night-shift shelf-stock 
ers at the local supermarket and lives in the modest 
house she has always lived in, caring for her aged moth 
er. No adventurous opportunities beckon in the futures 
of Sam or Lucille, or for most of the others in the bliss 
ful congregation we see, but they have now been put in 
direct contact with Jesus and are saved for eternity, 
beloved members in good standing of the community of 
the born again. They have turned over a new leaf, in a 
most dramatic ceremony, and they face their otherwise 
uninspiring lives refreshed and uplifted. Their lives now 
tell a story, and it's a chapter of the Greatest Story Ever 
Told. Can you imagine anything else they could buy 
with those $20 bills they deposit in the collection plate 
that would be remotely as valuable to them? 
Certainly, comes the reply. They could donate their 
money to a religion that was honest, and that actually 
used their sacrifices to help others who were still needi 
er. Or they could join any secular organization that put 
their free time, energy, and money to effective use ame 
liorating some of the world's ills. Perhaps the main rea 
son that religions do most of the heavy lifting in large 
parts of America is that people really do want to help 
others-and secular organizations have failed to com 
pete with religions for the allegiance of ordinary people. 
That's important, but it's the easy part of the answer, 
leaving untouched the hard part: What should we do 
about those whom we honestly think are being conned? 
Should we leave them to their comforting illusions or 
blow the whistle? 
Dilemmas like that are all too farniliar in somewhat 
different contexts, of course. Should the sweet old lady 
in the nursing home be told that her son has just been 
B6 THE CHRONICLE OF HIGHER EDUCATION 
sent to prison? Should the awkward 12-year-old boy 
who wasn't cut from the baseball team be told about 
the arm-twisting that persuaded the coach to keep him 
on the squad? In spite of ferocious differences of opin 
ion about other moral issues, there seems to be some 
thing approaching consensus that it is cruel and mali 
cious to interfere with the life-enhancing illusions of 
others-unless those illusions are themselves the cause 
of even greater ills. The disagreements come over what 
those greater ills might be-and that leads to the break 
down of the whole rationale. Keeping secrets from peo 
ple for their own good can often be wise, but it takes 
only one person to give away a secret, and since there 
are disagreements about which cases warrant discre 
tion, the result is an unsavory miasma of hypocrisy,lies, 
and frantic, but fruitless, attempts at distraction. 
What if Gortner were to con a cadre of sincere evan 
gelical preachers into doing his dirty work? Would their 
innocence change the equation and give genuine mean 
ing to the lives of those whose sacrifices they encour 
aged and collected? Or are all evangelical preachers 
just as false as Gortner? Certainly Muslims think so, 
even though they are generally too discreet to say it. 
And Roman Catholics think that Jews are just as delud 
ed, and Protestants think that Catholics are wasting 
their time and energy on a largely false religion, and so 
forth. All Muslims? All Catholics? All Protestants? All 
Jews? Of course not. There are vocal minorities in every 
faith who blurt it out, like the Catholic movie star Mel 
Gibson, who was interviewed by Peter J. Boyer in a 
2003 profile in The New Yorker. Boyer asked him if 
Protestants are denied eternal salvation. 
"There is no salvation for those outside the Church," 
Gibson replied. "I believe it." He explained: "Put it this 
way. My wife is a saint. She's a much better person than 
I am. Honestly. She's, like, Episcopalian, Church of Eng 
land. She prays, she believes in God, she knows Jesus, 
she believes in that stuff. And it's not fair if she doesn't 
make it, she's better than I am. But that is a pronounce 
ment from the chair. I go with it." 
Such remarks deeply embarrass two groups of 
Catholics: those who believe it but think it is best left 
unsaid, and those who don't believe it at all-no matter 
what "the chair" may pronounce. And which group of 
Catholics is larger, or more influential? That is utterly 
unknown and c\l!Tently unknowable, a part of the unsa 
vory miasma. 
It is equally unknown how many Muslims truly be 
lieve that all infidels deserve death, which is what the 
Koran undeniably says. Most Muslims, I would guess, 
are sincere in their insistence that the injunction that 
apostates be killed is to be disregarded, but it's discon 
certing, to say the least, that fear of being regarded as 
an apostate is apparently a major motivation in the Is 
lamic world. So it is not just we outsiders who are left 
guessing. 
One reason, free-floating or not, for such systemati 
cally masked creeds is to avoid-or at least postpone 
the collision between contradictory creeds that would 
otherwise oblige the devout to behave far more intoler 
antly than most people today want to behave. (It is al 
ways worth reminding ourselves that not so very long 
ago people were banished, tortured, and even executed 
for heresy and apostasy in the most "civilized" comers 
of Christian Europe.) 
So what is the prevai1ing attitude today among those 
who call themselves religious but vigorously advocate 
tolerance? There are tlrree main options: 
&#8226; The disingenuous Machiavellian: As a matter of 
political strategy, the time is not ripe for candid declara 
tions of religious superiority, so we should temporize 
and let sleeping dogs lie in hopes that those of other 
faiths can gently be brought around over the centuries. 
&#8226; The truly tolerant: It really doesn't matter which 
religion you swear allegiance to, as long as you have 
some religion. 
&#8226; The benign negJecters: Religion is just too dear to 
too many to think of discarding it, even though it really 
doesn't do any good and is simply an empty historical 
legacy we can afford to maintain until it quietly extin 
guishes itself sometime in the unforeseeable future. 
It is no use asking people which they choose, since 
the extremes are so undiplomatic we can predict in ad 
vance that most people will go for some version of ecu 
menical tolerance, whether they believe it or not. 
So we've got ourselves caught in a hypocrisy trap, and 
JANUARY 20, 2006 
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_2" n="2" type="page">
<p>there is no clear path out. Are we like the families in 
which the adults go through all the motions of believing 
in Santa Claus for the sake of the kids, and the kids all 
pretend still to believe in Santa Gaus so as not to spoil 
the adults' fun? If only our current predicament were as 
innocuous and even comical as that! In the adult world 
of religion, people are dying and killing, with the mod 
erates cowed into silence by the intransigence of the 
radicals in their own faiths, and many adherents afraid 
to acknowledge what they actually believe for fear of 
breaking Granny's heart, or offending their neighbors 
to the point of getting run out of town, or worse. 
If that is the precious meaning our lives are vouch 
safed thanks to our allegiance to one religion or anoth-
er, it is not such a bargain. Is that the best we can do? Is 
it not tragic that so many people around the world find 
themselves enlisted against their will in a conspiracy of 
silence? 
What alternatives are there? There are moderates 
who revere the tradition they were raised in, simply be 
cause it is their tradition, and who are prepared to cam 
paign, tentatively, for the details of their tradition, sim-
. ply because, in the marketplace of ideas, somebody 
should stick up for each tradition until we can sort out 
the good from the better and settle for the best we can 
find, all things considered. That is like allegiance to a 
sports team, and it, too, can give meaning to a life-if 
not taken too seriously. I am a Red Sox fan, simply be 
cause I grew up in the Boston area and have happy 
memories of Ted Williams, Jimmy Piersall, Carl Yas 
trzemski, Pudge FIsk, and \Vade Boggs, among others. 
My allegiance to the Red Sox is enthusiastic, but cheer 
fully arbitrary and undeluded. The Red Sox aren't my 
team because they are, in fact, the Best; they are the 
Best (in my eyes) because they are my team. 
JANUARY 20, 2006 
That is a kind of love, but not&#183; the rabid love that 
leads people to lie, and torture, and kill. 
I
N ORDER to adopt such a moderate position, how 
ever, you have to loosen your grip on the ab 
solutes that are apparently one of the main at 
tractions of many religious creeds. It isn't easy 
being moral, and it seems to be getting harder 
and harder these days. It used to be that most of the 
world's ills-disease, famine, war-were quite beyond 
the capacities of everyday people to ameliorate. There 
was nothing they could do about it, so people could ig 
nore the catastrophes on the other side of the globe-if 
they even knew about them-with a clear conscience. 
Living by a few simple, locally applicable maxims could 
more or less guarantee that one lived about as good a 
life as was possible at the time. No longer. 
Thanks to technology, what almost anybody can do 
has been multiplied a thousandfold, but our moral un 
derstanding about what we ought to do hasn't kept pace. 
You can have a test-tube baby or take a morning-after 
pill to keep from having a baby; you can satisfy your sex 
ual urges in the privacy of your room by downloading 
Internet pornography, or you can copy your favorite 
music free instead of buying it; you can keep your 
money in secret offshore bank accounts or purchase 
stock in cigarette companies that are exploiting impov 
erished third-world countries; and you can lay mine 
fields, smuggle nuclear weapons in suitcases, make nerve 
gas, and drop "smart bombs" with pinpoint accuracy. 
Also, you can arrange to have $100 a month automati 
cally sent from your bank account to provide education 
for 10 girls in an Islamic country who otherwise would 
not learn to read and write, or to benefit 100 malnour 
ished people, or provide medical care for AIDS sufferers 
in Africa. You can use the Internet to organize citizen 
monitoring of environmental ha2ards or to check the 
honesty and performance of government officials-or to 
spy on your neighbors. Now, what ought we to do? 
In the face of such truly imponderable questions, it is 
entirely reasonable to look for a short set of simple an 
swers. H.L. Mencken cynically said, "For every complex 
problem, there is a simple answer ... and it is wrong." 
But maybe he was wrong! Maybe one Golden Rule or 
the Ten Commandments or some other short list of ab 
solutely nonnegotiable Dos and Don'ts resolves all the 
predicaments just fine, once you figure out how to app(y 
them. Nobody would deny, however, that it is far from 
obvious how any of the favored rules or principles can 
be interpreted to fit all our quandaries. "Thou shalt not 
kill" is cited by religious opponents of the death penalty, 
and by proponents as well. The principle of the Sanctity 
of Human Life sounds bracingly clear and absolute: 
Every human life is equally sacred, equally inviolable; 
as with the king in chess, no price can be placed on it, 
since to lose it is to lose everything. But in fact we all 
know that life isn't, and can't be, like chess. There are 
multitudes of interfering "games" going on at once. 
What are we to do when more than one human life is at 
stake? If each life is infinitely valuable and none more 
valuable than another, how are we to dole out the few 
transplantable kidneys that are available, for instance? 
Modern technology only exacerbates the issues, which 
are ancient. Solomon faced tough choices with notable 
wisdom, and every mother who has ever had less than 
enough food for her own children (let alone her neigh 
bor's children) has had to confront the impracticality of 
applying the principle of the Sanctity of Human Life. 
S
URELY just about everybody has faced a moral 
dilemma and secretly wished, "If only some 
body-somebody I trusted-could tell me 
what to do!" Wouldn't that be morally inau 
thentic? Aren't we responsible for making our 
own moral decisions? Yes, but the virtues of "do it your 
self' moral reasoning have their limits, and if you de 
cide, after conscientious consideration, that your moral 
decision is to delegate further moral decisions in your 
life to a trusted expert, then you have made your own 
moral decision. You have decided to take advantage of 
Continued on Following Page 
In the adult world 
of religion, people 
~~_~_~g __ ~~U~jlE~gL __ . _____ _ 
with the moderates 
cowed into silence 
!?l'_.!h~j_~tran~ige~~~ ____ .... _____ ._ 
of the radicals 
in their own faiths. 
THE CHRONICLE OF HIGHER EDUCATION B7 
</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="page_3" n="3" type="page">
<p>B8 THE CHRONICLE OF HIGHER EDUCATION 
Continued From Preceding Page 
the division of labor that civilization 
makes possible and get the help of ex 
pert specialists. 
We applaud the wisdom of that course 
in all other important areas of decision 
making (don't try to be your own doctor, 
the lawyer who represents himself has a 
fool for a client, and so forth). Even in 
the case of political decisions, like which 
way to vote, the policy of delegation can 
be defended. When my wife and I go to a 
town meeting, I know that she has stud 
ied the issues so much more assiduously 
than I that I routinely follow her lead, 
voting the way she tells me. Even if I'm 
not sure why, I have plenty of evidence 
_ for my conviction that, if we did take the 
time and energy to thrash it all out, she'd 
persuade me that, all things considered, 
her opinion was correct. Is that a derelic 
tion of my duties as a citizen? I don't 
think so, but it does depend on my hav 
ing good grounds for trusting her judg 
ment. Love is not enough. 
That's why those who have an unques 
tioning faith in the correctness of the 
moral teachings of their religion are a 
problem: If they haven't conscientiously 
considered, on their own, whether their 
pastors or priests or rabbis or imams are 
worthy of such delegated authority over 
theiJ; lives, then they are taking a person 
ally immoral stand. 
That is perhaps the most shocking im 
plication of my inquiry into the role reli 
gion plays in our lives, and I do not 
shrink from it, even though it may offend 
many who think of themselves as deeply 
moral. It is commonly supposed that it is 
entirely exemplary to adopt the moral 
teachings of one's own religion without 
question because-to put it simply-it is 
the word of God (as interpreted, always, 
by the specialists to whom one has dele 
gated authority). I am urging, on the con 
trary, that anybody who professes that a 
particular point of moral conviction is 
not discussable, not debatable, not nego 
tiable, simply because it is the word of 
God, or because the Bible says so, or be 
cause "that is what all Muslims (Hindus, 
Sikhs . .. ) believe, and I am a Muslim 
(Hindu, Sikh . . . )" should be seen to be 
making it impossible for the rest of us to 
take their views seriously, excusing them 
selves from the moral conversation, inad 
vertently acknowledging that their own 
views are not conscientiously maintained 
and deserve no further hearing. 
The argument is straightforward. Sup 
pose I have a friend, Fred, who is (in my 
carefully considered opinion) always 
right. If I tell you I'm against stem-cell 
research because "my friend Fred says 
it's wrong, and that's all there is to it," 
you will just look at me as if I were miss 
ing the point of the discussion. I have not 
given you a reason that, in good faith, I" 
could expect you to appreciate. Suppose 
you believe that stem-cell research is 
wrong because God has told you so. 
Even if you are right-that is, even if 
God does exist and has, personally, told 
you that stem-cell research is wrong 
you cannot reasonably expect others 
who do not share your faith or experi 
ence to accept that as a reason. The fact 
that your faith is so strong that you can 
not do otherwise just shows (if you really 
can't) that you are disabled for moral 
persuasion, a sort of robotic slave to a 
meme that you are unable to evaluate. 
And if you reply that you can, but you 
won't consider reasons for and against 
your conviction (because it is God's 
word, and it would be sacrilegious even 
to consider whether it might be in error), 
you avow your willful refusal to abide by 
the minimal conditions of rational dis 
cussion. Either way, your declarations of 
your deeply held views are posturings 
that are out of place, part of the problem, 
not part of the solution, and we others 
will just have to work around you as best 
we can. 
Notice that my stand involves no dis 
respect and no prejudging of the possi 
bility that God has told you. If God has 
told you, then part of your problem is 
convincing others, to whom God has not 
(yet) spoken. If you refuse or are unable 
to attempt that, you are actually letting 
your God down, in the guise of demon 
strating your helpless love. You can with 
draw from the discussion if you must 
that is your right-but then don't blame 
us if we don't "get it." 
Many deeply religious people have all 
along been eager to defend their convic 
tions in the court of reasonable inquiry 
and persuasion. They will have no diffi 
culty at all with my observations-aside 
from confronting the diplomatic decision 
of whether they will join me in trying to 
convince their less reasonable co-reli 
gionists that they are making matters 
worse for their religion by their intransi 
gence. That is one of the most intractable 
moral. problems confronting the world 
today. Every religion-aside from a neg 
ligible scattering of truly toxic cults-has 
a healthy population of ecumenicaJ 
minded people who are eager to reach 
out to people of other faiths, or no faith 
at all, and consider the moral quandaries 
of the world on a rational basis. 
But such well-intentioned people are 
singnlarly ineffective in dealing with the 
more radical members of their own 
faiths. In many instances they are, rightly, 
terrified of them. Moderate Muslims 
have so far been utterly unable to turn 
the' tide of Islamic opinion against Wah 
habists and other extremists, but moder 
ate Christians and Jews and Hindus have 
been equally feckless in countering the 
outrageous demands and acts of their 
own radical elements. 
It is time for the reasonable adherents 
of all faiths to find the courage and stam 
ina to reverse the tradition that honors 
helpless love of God-in any tradition. 
Far from being honorable, it is not even 
excusable. It is shameful. Here is what we 
should say to people who follow such a 
tradition: There is only one way to re 
spect the substance of any purported 
God-given moral edict. Consider it con 
scientiously in the full light of reason, 
using all the evidence at our command. 
No God pleased by displays of unreason 
ing love is worthy of worship. 
Daniel C Dennett is a university profes 
sor and director of the Center for Cogni 
tive Studies at Tufts University. This essay 
is adapted from his book Breaking the 
Spell: Religion as a Natural Phenome 
non, to be published this month by 
Viking. Copyright &#169; 2()()6 by Daniel C 
Dennett. 
JANUARY 20, 2006 
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
